aimaina hyouden koshiraete hitatteru no
I create a vague critical biography and wallow in it
seisei saisai nani o mada matteru no
Generation after generation, time after time,
what are you still waiting for
itsunomanika hitori ni natta
I was all alone before I knew it
tameiki hitotsu haite nageite
Breathed out a single sigh and lamented
jounetsu moyashita ano koro o
Those days of burning passion
shinketsu sosoide torimodosunda
Put your heart and soul into getting them back
en de tsunagareba kono hibi mo
Bind these days with bonds and perhaps
suteru hodo koware tenaidarou
They can be salvaged
ayumi o tomenaide
Don't stop walking forward
kibou o sutenaide
Don't give up hope
douka furimuite
Please look back
dou ka kimiyo
Please, if you would
jin jin kokoro ga itamunara
If the heart throbs with pain
kannen no ori o uchiyaburu nda
Break through the ideology that imprisons you
enen tsukihi wa megurukedo
Time goes around for eternity
suteru ni wa yami ga asaidarou
But the darkness within you is still shallow,
not worth throwing it all away
jounetsu moyashita ano koro o
Those days of burning passion
shinketsu sosoide torimodosu nda
Put your heart and soul into getting them back
ai o wakeaeba kono hibi mo
If we love each other then surely these days will
mouichido kimi o terasudarou
Once again, shine upon you
There they are!
It figures they'd be here.
(サクラ)いた。
(カカシ)やっぱりここか。
Thanks, Sakura.
Sakura...
(ナルト)ありがとう サクラちゃん。
Never mind me...
Stay quiet now.
(サスケ)サクラ 俺は…。
I need to concentrate.
今は黙って。 集中するから。
I'm sorry...
Sorry? For what?
すまなかった。
すまなかったって… なにが？
For everything...
You should be.
今までの…。
Really... you...
ほんとよ…。
まったく。
damn...
idiot!
しゃーんなろーよ… バカ。
He's finally back.
やっと戻ったね。
Naruto...
I've been thinking about
what you once said to me.
＜ナルト このときの俺は→
あの お前の言葉を
思い出していた。
When we were together,
you wondered if it was
how having a brother would feel...
俺といるとき 兄弟がいるのは
こんな感じなのかと思うと…＞
Now, finally...
I think I know what you meant.
＜ その感覚が このとき
やっとわかったんだ＞
I felt how my mother, father,
and brother Itachi suffered.
＜父や母 それに兄弟だった
イタチの苦しみや思いが→
In that same way...
俺に伝わってきたのと
同じように＞
Naruto...
I'm sure I will start to feel your pain
and your emotions...
＜今は ナルト…
お前の苦しみや思いが→
You never cut me off.
同じように伝わってくるだろうと。
You always kept me in your thoughts.
お前は 決して俺を切らず ずっと
俺の心に近づいてきてくれた＞
Naruto...
(ヒナタ)ナルト君…。
SHIKAKU NARA
INOICHI YAMANAKA
You'd have been justified if
you'd come at me with hatred...
＜俺に 憎しみをぶつけてきても
おかしくなかったはずなのに→
Instead, you always called me
your friend.
NEJI HYUGA
お前は ずっと
俺のことを友だと言った＞
And I tried to betray
even those feelings...
＜俺は その思いすら
切ろうとしたってのに＞
As I explained,
it's the village policy.
Only those authorized are allowed
at the interview.
(ゲンマ)ですから 里の方針で
ナルトへの接見は→
All others, please leave!
関係者以外
お断りしておりますので→
What? Do you know
how far I traveled?
どうか お引き取りください！
Let us see him, just once!
おい！ なんだよ…
遠路はるばる来たんだぞ!!
– Yeah!
It's the village policy...
ひと目でいいから会わせろ！
そうだ そうだ！
– Let us see Naruto!
(コテツ)ですから
これは 里の方針で…。
Please don't push! It's dangerous.
(３人)ナルトさんに会わせろ！
(イズモ)ちょっと！
危ないですから 押さないで。
This should take care
of the successorship.
(綱手)これで とりあえず
引き継ぎは全部だ。
It's a lot of paper.
Yeah...
はぁ… すごい量ですね。
Anyway, congratulations on becoming
the Sixth Hokage, Kakashi.
まぁな。 六代目火影 就任
おめでとう カカシ。
Thank you.
I just wonder...
Can I do this?
ありがとうございます。
You'll manage. After all, I did.
でも… 私に務まりますかね？
まぁ なんとかなるだろう。
私でも なんとかなったしな。
I'll do my best.
Excuse me.
頑張ってみます。
(シズネ)失礼します。
Status report:
The Raikage's entourage and
(シズネ)報告
雷影様ご一行に続いて→
the Kazekage's entourage
have arrived.
May I escort them to Naruto, too?
風影様ご一行も
お見えになられました。
You may.
ナルト君のもとへ
案内しても かまいませんか？
(２人)あぁ。
フフッ…。
Further...
I have a request.
それと…。
(シカマル)お願いがあります。
I see, Shikamaru.
I understand your intentions.
(カカシ)なるほど。 シカマル…
お前のもくろみは わかった。
I want to get some experience
and improve my prospects too.
(シカマル)俺自身も 将来を見すえて
経験値を上げておきたいっすから。
All that's left is him.
A ton of visitors are asking about him.
あとは あいつか。
Suddenly he's Mr Popular.
(綱手)よそからの訪問者も
絶えんようだし→
That's all right.
たいした人気者だ！
He's not the type to get carried away.
大丈夫です。 有頂天に溺れる隙は
与えませんから。
Hey! Gaara!
おっ！ 我愛羅。
Naruto...
(我愛羅)ナルト…。
You... saved me yet again.
お前に また救われたな。
And us.
(エー)我々もだ。
How's your wound?
It's about what you'd guess.
(カンクロウ)で… ケガの具合は？
Can't say I'm in the best shape.
まぁ 見てのとおりだ。
Then, what'll you do about that arm?
大丈夫とは言えねえけど。
(テマリ)それで
その腕は どうなるんだ？
Oh, Grandma Tsunade said
something about
harvesting cells from Hashirama,
the First Hokage, or whatever.
あぁ 綱手のばあちゃんの話だと→
なんか 初代火影の柱間細胞を
培養だか なんだかで→
She's gonna fuse them with mine,
I suppose?
I don't really understand.
俺の細胞と掛け合わせるらしい。
Will it be as good as new?
なんのことか
よく わかんねえけど。
Yeah! I think.
また 元どおりになるのか？
あぁ たぶんな。
I'm here today so they can check.
I see...
今日は
その検査のためだけに来てんだ。
Naruto is the Ninja World's sun!
His right hand's a precious companion!
そうか…。
♪♪(キラービー)「ナルトは忍世界の太陽」
Losing it is devastation! Yay!
♪♪「右腕 大事な相棒」
So to get it back intact!
Use Hashirama's cells, in fact.
♪♪「それをなくすは 敗北 イエー」
♪♪「取り戻すための対応」
It'll be as good as new, Jack! Yay!
♪♪「柱間細胞 培養」
♪♪「元に戻るは 最高。 アッ！ イエー」
What's he up to?
アハハハハ！
やつは 今 どうしている？
I really don't wanna say much.
それについては
あんま話したくねえな…。
SEAL
I promised I wouldn't.
I see.
口止めもされてっし。
そうか…。
S-Sensei!
Don't cry, Lee!
(リー)せ… 先生！
(ガイ)泣くな リー。
Even if the bright days of youth end here,
there is still a future for me!
若く
まぶしい青春は終わろうとも→
The sun that shines bright!
俺には まだ先がある。
The sweltering heat!
ギラギラ輝く太陽
モンモンとうだる暑さ。
The red-hot days of
summer are here!
紅く燃えたぎる→
円熟の朱夏の季節の到来だ！
O-Oww...
Guy Sensei!
《あっ 痛い…》
I'm inspired!
What a brilliant way of thinking!
うお～！ ガイ先生
感動です！
Oh yuck...
なんて
すばらしい考え方でしょう！
NINJA ACADEMY
《テンテン : うざ…》
Shikamaru...
I hear you're
the Hokage's personal assistant.
シカマル お前 火影の側近補佐に
就いたんだって？
Well, yeah.
I have to keep moving forward too.
まあな。
俺も前に進まねえとな。
So why'd you ask me to
come to the Academy?
で なんでアカデミーに俺を？
Iruka Sensei? And Kakashi Sensei?
え？ イルカ先生と カカシ先生。
More like Lord Hokage now.
先生っていうか火影な。
Huh?! When did that—?!
You must have seen all the messages
that came in this morning.
えっ ええ～！
いつの間に！?
I had no idea...
今朝 内々の伝達あったろ。
Don't worry about it.
知らなかった～。
So what do I call you?
まあ いいけどよ。
Kakashi Hokage?
え～と じゃあ
何て呼べばいいんだ？
Hokage Kakashi Teacher?
カカシ火影？
火影カカシティーチャーとか？
Well, let's decide that later.
まあ それは
後で決めてもらうとして。
Naruto!
ナルト。
You never got to take
the Chunin Exam, right?
お前 中忍試験すら
受けてなかったな。
No...
Naruto Uzumaki!
うん。
うずまきナルト。
I, the Sixth Hokage, hereby grant you
the rank of Jonin of
the Village Hidden in the Leaves!
六代目火影の名の下に→
お前を木ノ葉隠れの里
上忍に任命する。
... is what I'd like to tell you.
But there's something
you must complete before that.
と言いたいところなんだが→
そのためには
クリアしなきゃならんことがある。
The educational materials
you'll be needing.
You mean...?
(イルカ)今のお前に必要な教材だ。
Yes, you have study.
これって…。
ま いわゆる勉強だ。
Study?!
No way!
べ 勉強だと～
イヤだ～！
No way, no way!
If I'm gonna have to study,
I'll just stay a genin!
ヤダ ヤダ ヤダ！
Hold on, Naruto.
勉強するくれえなら
下忍のままでいいってばよ！
There's no shortcut to
becoming the Hokage!
(カカシ)待て ナルト。
(木ノ葉丸)火影までの道程に
近道なんてないぞ コレ！
Got it?!
Naruto...
I don't have to tell you
ナルト お前の忍としての実力は→
that your skill as a shinobi
is second to none.
もはや
俺が語るまでもないだろう。
However, if your goal is
to become the Hokage...
You must learn how to stand
above others and lead them.
だが この先
火影を目指すなら→
まずは人の上に立ち→
導くことを
学ばなければならない。
You catch on fast,
and for most things,
それに お前は頭が回るし→
Shikamaru will support you
with his resourcefulness.
たいていの知略は
シカマルがサポートしてくれるだろうが→
Still, a minimum of learning
and knowledge is essential.
それでも最低限の知識
教養は必要だ。
We're rivals who both aim to
become Hokage, right?!
俺たち
火影を目指すライバルだろう コレ。
THE HISTORY OF SHINOBI
VOLUME 1
ああ。
You really dug in, Naruto.
Two more years,
and you can become a jonin.
頑張ったな ナルト。
So long...
あと２年もすれば
上忍なれるぞ。
Okay, let's call it a day
なげえ～…。
and go grab some ramen.
よし 今日は終わりにして
ラーメンでも食いに行くか。
Yes!
NINJA ACADEMY
やった～！
Now what toppings should I choose?
さ～てと トッピングは
何にしようかなっと。
Hey, don't get carried away.
フフ こらこら
調子に乗るなよ。
It's all thanks to you, Iruka Sensei.
Huh?
イルカ先生のおかげだ。
ええ？
Do you remember that day?
あの日のこと 覚えてる？
Hmm?
That night, Sensei...
ああ。
あのとき 先生→
You accepted me.
It was the first time ever.
俺のことを
認めてくれただろう？
That's why I'm here today.
初めてだったんだ。
だから 今の俺があるんだ。
If no one acknowledged me
and I stayed the way I was...
もし誰からも
認めてもらえねえで→
Maybe I would've resented the village
and everyone in it, and gone wild.
あのままだったら→
里や みんなを恨んで
ムチャクチャになってたかもしんねえ。
But your words
that night changed me.
でも あのとき 先生の言葉で
俺は変われたんだ。
But Naruto is different.
He's...
((けど ナルトは違う。
He's an exceptional student
and I acknowledge him!
あいつは
あいつは この俺が認めた→
He is...
優秀な生徒だ。
Naruto Uzumaki of the Hidden Leaf!
(あいつは 木ノ葉隠れの里の
うずまきナルトだ))
Thank you, Iruka Sensei.
ありがとう イルカ先生。
That... that does it!
Today, you can have
all the toppings you want!
しかたないな。
今日は奮発 フルトッピングでいいぞ。
Awright!
やった～！
Sasuke...
サスケ。
I'll be blunt.
By rights, you should be
in prison right now.
But we have heard your plea and
(カカシ)まっ はっきり言って
本来ならお前は→
all your actions up to now
have been pardoned.
強制的に
投獄される身だったから→
Breaking the jutsu
for the Infinite Tsukuyomi
お前の望みが聞き入れられ
今までの行為が免責されたのは→
played a big part in the decision.
As well as the fact that I happened
to become the Sixth Hokage,
無限月読解術による功績が
大きいってことだったけどさ→
and that Naruto,
the key figure in ending the war,
六代目火影が俺になったことや→
testified on your behalf.
Don't forget that.
この戦争終結の立役者になった
ナルトの嘆願によるところが→
And please don't get too reckless.
Otherwise, I'll be held responsible.
大きかったこと 忘れないように。
Understood. Thank you.
これからは あまりムチャしないでよ。
Must you go?
俺の責任になっちゃうから。
The artificial arm that
Lady Tsunade is creating
ああ すまない。
from Lord Hashirama's cells will soon...
どうしても行っちゃうの？
I need time to understand
my feelings.
綱手様が柱間様の細胞で
造った義手も もう少しで…。
How I should view the shinobi world,
this world.
今の俺なら この忍界が→
Perhaps I'll be able to see things
I couldn't see before.
この世界が どう見えるのか→
Things that can't be seen
unless I do this.
知りたいんだ。
今まで見逃してきたことも
見えそうな気がする。
Also, there's something
I'm worried about.
このままでなければ見えない
何かが…。
それに 気になってることも
あるしな。
What if I said... I'd go with you?
私も… ついていくって言ったら？
This is a trip to atone for my sins.
My sins have
nothing to do with you.
罪を償う旅でもある。
Nothing to do with me...?
お前は俺の罪とは関係ない。
関係ないか…。
Maybe next time.
Thank you.
また今度な。
ありがとう。
I didn't think
you'd come to see me off.
Here.
お前は見送りには
来ないと思ったが。
You kept that thing?
ん。
You sacrificed your arm to stop me.
お前 まだこんなもん。
Thanks to you, I found salvation.
＜片腕を失ってまで
俺を止めてくれた。
Once, all we did was clash
with each other.
お前のおかげで俺は救われた。
But now, we share each other's pain.
いがみ合ってた
ちっぽけな俺たちが→
After all my travels
through the world,
今は互いの心を
痛み合うことができる。
I came to the conclusion
that this sharing of pain
そして 旅を通して
世界を見てこう思った。
can perhaps be applied to something
much bigger than just us.
このことは俺たちだけじゃなく→
But I can't do things like you.
もっと大きなものにも
言えることなのかもしれないと。
Things don't go that smoothly,
だが お前のようには
なかなかできるものじゃない。
as you and I know more than anyone...
The bigger something is, the harder.
そう簡単にはいかないだろう。
俺たち自身がそうだったように→
I'm returning this.
大きなものなら なおさらな＞
I'll hang on to it...
これを返す。
... until our real match.
お前との本当の勝負まで…。
This idea is almost a prayer.
To keep enduring, no matter what,
until things come to pass.
取っておいてやるよ。
＜ それは祈りにも似た思いだ。
And for we who must endure,
それでも それができるまで
耐え忍んでいく。
perhaps that's what it means...
... to be a ninja.
その様を任された者たち。
それが俺たち 忍者なのかもな＞
boku ni wa wakaru nda uso o tsuite iru kimi ga
I can tell when you're lying
naite ii yo koko ni zutto irukara
It's okay to cry because I'll always be here
sekaijuu ni koborete iru hontou no ai no kimochi
Feelings of true love spills out throughout the world
sagashidashite miushinatte yoake ga kuru no matteru
We search for it but lose it, while waiting for daybreak
migi no hoshi ni wa boku no namae o tsukete
The star on the right will bear my name
kimi ga yonde okureyo
Will you call out to it?
hidari no hoshi ni wa kimi no namae ga ne
The star on the left will bear your name
niau yo zutto soba ni irukara
It's perfect, because we'll always be together
Long ago, there was a fox spirit.
This fox had nine tails.
The fox was sealed inside
a shinobi's child
＜ヒルゼン : 昔 妖狐ありけり。
and over time,
they became close friends.
その狐 九つの尾あり。
狐 封印されし忍の童→
Then a new calamity occurred.
The Ten Tails was resurrected.
これと長きにわたり 寄り添いて→
But the child grew up to be a shinobi,
いつしか 友となりけり。
and the fox spirit, the child, and the clans
joined to seal away the Ten Tails.
新たな厄災 十尾復活せしが→
忍の童 忍の者となり→
This son of the Fourth Hokage
妖狐と忍の輩 一丸となりて→
into whom the fox spirit
was sealed, was named...
これを封印せしめる。
Naruto Uzumaki.
妖狐封印 忍の者→
四代目火影の子にして
名をうずまきナルトと申す＞
Hmm... Now this looks delicious.
Well, it's the fish I caught.
‘Course it's gonna be good!
I will make you strong.
In times of danger,
I will risk my life to protect you.
Brother Neji...
Next time on Naruto Shippuden:
"NARUTO - HINATA"